Department of Biological Sciences fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
Department of Biological Sciences fonds
1962 - 1989
F-5
5.25 m of textual records
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
Department of Biological Sciences
The Department of Biological Sciences was established in 1965 as a department in the Faculty of Science. From its inception, the department offered a broad curriculum leading to B.Sc., M.Sc., and Ph.D. degrees. The overall mission of the Department was to provide instruction in Biology and, by research, to increase the knowledge base in Biological Sciences. This mission encapsulated four broad areas of responsibility: to provide broad-based undergraduate instruction in modern biology; to provide graduate training leading to Master of Pest Management (M.P.M.), M.Sc. and Ph.D. degrees; to provide a work environment and facilities for faculty, researchers, and graduate students; and to provide for expansion and development of research and graduate training and to foster the development of intra- and interdepartmental Centres and Institutes designed to promote collaborative research and training. With the opening of the Pestology Centre in 1967, it began its specialization in pest management and the role of nurturing an international centre for excellence in research and teaching in the field.
The Department was administered by the Chair and two standing committees: Departmental Undergraduate Curriculum Committee (DUCC) and the Departmental Graduate Studies Committee (DGSC). The Chair was responsible for the overall administration of the Department, including the operational budget, faculty tenure and salary recommendations, teaching assignments and representation of the Department. The DUCC was responsible for the development, implementation and monitoring of the undergraduate program. The DGSC was responsible for graduate admission recommendations, monitoring the progress of graduate students, and developing criteria and methodology for student evaluation for purposes of scholarships. By 1990, two further committees had been added: the Departmental Tenure Committee and the Committee on Space. The Departmental Assistant and Lab Coordinator were responsible for much of day-to-day administration of the Department. The Departmental Assistant reported to the Chair, who in turn reported to the Dean of Science. The Pestology Centre, renamed the Centre for Pest Management in the 1980s, was headed by a Director, who was responsible for the planning and development of programs within the Centre and the promotion of external relations. The Director was also actively involved in a number of international organizations for biological control and entomological research. The Director reported to the Department Chair.
The Department was involved in or associated with university interdisciplinary research institutes which conducted both research and instruction. These included the Centre for Pest Management and the Institute of Molecular Biology and Biochemistry (IMBB). The IMBB was established in 1987 as an interdisciplinary graduate research institute, and its members held appointments in Biological Sciences and/or Chemistry. The Department was also affiliated with several bodies responsible for research. These research groups included the Behavioural Ecology Research Group (BERG), the Chemical Ecology Research Group (CERG), the Institute of Aquaculture Research (IAR), the Institute of Quaternary Research (IQR), the R.H. Wright Institute for Sensory Science (WISS), and the Western Canadian Universities Marine Biological Society (WCUMBS).
From its inception the department expanded greatly in terms of the size of its faculty and the number of programs offered. In 1965, the department consisted of six faculty, and increased to thirty by 1969 and forty by 1994. A significant addition to its program offerings was the establishment in 1973 of the Master of Pest Management degree program.
The first Director of the Centre for Pest Management was Dr. Bryan P. Beirne, who served until 1980. In 1986, Dr. J.P. Manfred Mackauer became the new Director, and he was succeeded by Dr. Zamir Punja in 1993.
published
Full
Revised
Title of the fonds is based on the name of the department.
The fonds of the Department of Biological Sciences consists of records created and received in the course of the administration of the department and the carrying out of its functions of providing instruction and promoting research. The activities documented include the administration of the department and its facilities; departmental, faculty, and external meetings; research proposals and funding applications; correspondence with university and external bodies and persons; curriculum and program planning, development and delivery; and the promotion and advertisement of the department's curriculum, programs and activities. The types of documents include meeting agenda and minutes, correspondence, directives, photographs, published materials, and research papers.
The titles and arrangement of series were provided by the archivist.
Srivastava, Lalit M.; Nair, Karun K.; Mackauer, Manfred; Webster, John M.; Geen, Glen H.; Nelson, C. Donald
The records of the department were transferred to the University Records Centre between 1981 and 1987.
As of January 2012, 7 cm of additional material have been accessioned but not yet processed. Please consult the archivist for information about using these materials; restrictions may apply. Further accruals are expected.
Consult the inventory of the Faculty of Science fonds, F-24.
Access restrictions apply in accordance with British Columbia's Freedom of Information and Protection of Privacy Act. Consult the appropriate series level descriptions and the archivist.
File lists are available.
- Chairman's correspondence and reports, 1965 - 1987; F-5-1; 85 cm of textual records
  published
  The series consists of records relating to the administrative and operational activities and interests of the department Chairman, including research, funding, relations with external bodies including the federal and provincial governments, proposals for new programs and courses, the Bamfield Marine Station and the Master of Pest Management program. Record types include circulars, correspondence, directives, reports and working papers. For a list of correspondents (as reflected in file titles), see Access Points below.
  Canada. Department of Agriculture; Western Canadian Universities Marine Biological Station; British Columbia. Ministry of Eduation, Science and Technology; Computing Services; Continuing Studies; Centre for Pest Management; National Research Council; Natural Science and Engineering Research Council; Environmental Health and Safety; Centre for Resource Management; Biochemistry Committee; Chinese Academy of Sciences; Centre for Online and Distance Education; President's Advisory Committee on University Priorities; Resource Management Committee
  - Canada department of agriculture, 1965; F-5-1-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 5-1)
    Textual records
    Pending review
  - Bamfield Marine Station, 1974 - 1977; F-5-1-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 5-1)
  - Bamfield Marine Station, 1977 - 1981; F-5-1-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 5-1)
  - Bamfield review - Director, 1980 - 1981; F-5-1-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 5-1)
  - Ministry of Education, Science and Technology, 1979; F-5-1-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 5-1)
  - Computing Centre, 1977 - 1980; F-5-1-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 5-1)
  - Continuing Studies, 1974 - 1981; F-5-1-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 5-1)
  - Environmental Toxicology, 1978 - 1981; F-5-1-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 5-1)
  - Master of Pest Management (MPM) program, 1974 - 1980; F-5-1-0-0-9 (Archival box - small 5-2)
  - Master of Pest Management (MPM) program, 1979 - 1982; F-5-1-0-0-10 (Archival box - small 5-2)
  - New programs in Science, new courses, 1977 - 1979; F-5-1-0-0-11 (Archival box - small 5-2)
  - National Research Council (NRC), 1976 - 1978; F-5-1-0-0-12 (Archival box - small 5-2)
  - NRC/Nuffield Visiting Lectureship, 1977 - 1978; F-5-1-0-0-13 (Archival box - small 5-2)
  - Natural Science and Engineering Research Council (NSERC), 1980 - 1982; F-5-1-0-0-14 (Archival box - small 5-2)
  - Natural Science and Engineering Research Council (NSERC), 1978 - 1980; F-5-1-0-0-15 (Archival box - small 5-2)
  - Occupational Health and Safety, 1978 - 1980; F-5-1-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 5-3)
  - Off-campus courses, 1975 - 1976; F-5-1-0-0-17 (Archival box - standard 5-3)
  - Research support and development, 1976 - 1982; F-5-1-0-0-18 (Archival box - standard 5-3)
  - Resource management, 1977 - 1981; F-5-1-0-0-19 (Archival box - standard 5-3)
  - Resource management, 1974 - 1976; F-5-1-0-0-20 (Archival box - standard 5-3)
  - Science Research Fund, 1975 - 1980; F-5-1-0-0-21 (Archival box - standard 5-4)
  - Workloads - faculty, 1975 - 1979; F-5-1-0-0-22 (Archival box - standard 5-4)
  - Agrogen Biotechnologies Inc., 1987; F-5-1-0-0-23 (Archival box - standard 5-27)
  - Analytical facilities, 1970 - 1982; F-5-1-0-0-24 (Archival box - standard 5-27)
  - Aquaculture, 1984 - 1987; F-5-1-0-0-25 (Archival box - standard 5-27)
  - Biochemistry Committee, 1974 - 1984; F-5-1-0-0-26 (Archival box - standard 5-27)
  - Biochemistry Program, 1984 - 1985; F-5-1-0-0-27 (Archival box - standard 5-27)
  - Biotechnology, 1980 - 1986; F-5-1-0-0-28 (Archival box - standard 5-28)
  - Chinese Academy of Science, 1981 - 1985; F-5-1-0-0-29 (Archival box - standard 5-28)
  - Computing Centre, 1980 - 1982; F-5-1-0-0-30 (Archival box - standard 5-28)
  - Co-operative education, 1978 - 1985; F-5-1-0-0-31 (Archival box - standard 5-28)
  - Environmental toxicology, 1980 - 1981; F-5-1-0-0-32 (Archival box - standard 5-28)
  - Industrial Advisor, 1979 - 1980; F-5-1-0-0-33 (Archival box - standard 5-28)
  - Marine Sciences Program, 1977 - 1983; F-5-1-0-0-34 (Archival box - standard 5-29)
  - Distance education, 1977 - 1986; F-5-1-0-0-35 (Archival box - standard 5-29)
  - Fund for Excellence, 1986; F-5-1-0-0-36 (Archival box - standard 5-29)
  - Programs of Distinction, 1977 - 1986; F-5-1-0-0-37 (Archival box - standard 5-29)
  - Off-campus courses, 1977 - 1980; F-5-1-0-0-38 (Archival box - standard 5-29)
  - Shrum Chair, 1984 - 1987; F-5-1-0-0-39 (Archival box - standard 5-29)
  - WCUMBS Academic Committee, 1982 - 1983; F-5-1-0-0-40 (Archival box - standard 5-29)
  - WCUMBS Academic Committee, 1984 - 1985; F-5-1-0-0-41 (Archival box - standard 5-29)
  - New programs in Science - new courses, 1980 - 1985; F-5-1-0-0-42 (Archival box - standard 5-30)
  - Bio-Bull newsletter, 1975 - 1976; F-5-1-0-0-43 (Archival box - standard 5-30)
  - Policies and procedures - proposed, 1978 - 1985; F-5-1-0-0-44 (Archival box - standard 5-30)
  - President's Advisory Committee of University Priorities, 1984; F-5-1-0-0-45 (Archival box - standard 5-30)
- Research grant applications, 1965 - 1983; F-5-2; 29 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to departmental research grants and projects funded from both governmental and non-governmental sources. It includes correspondence, research proposals, grant applications, and working papers. Files are arranged in alphabetical order by name of faculty member; for names, see Access Points below.
  Albright, Lawrence J.; Barlow, John S.; Borden, John H.; Druehl, Louis; Geen, Glen H.; McClaren, Milton; Nair, Karun K.; Sadleir, R.M.; Srivastava, Lalit M.; Turnbull, Albert
  - Research grants - A, 1967 - 1981; F-5-2-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 5-4)
  - NSERC research grants - A, 1967 - 1983; F-5-2-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 5-4)
  - NSERC research grants - B, 1967 - 1983; F-5-2-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 5-4)
  - Research grants - B, 1966 - 1975; F-5-2-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 5-4)
  - Research grants - D, 1966 - 1982; F-5-2-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 5-5)
  - NSERC research grants - G, 1966 - 1980; F-5-2-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 5-5)
  - Research grants - G, 1968 - 1983; F-5-2-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 5-5)
  - NSERC research grants - M, 1967 - 1978; F-5-2-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 5-5)
  - NSERC research grants - N, 1967 - 1980; F-5-2-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 5-5)
  - NSERC research grants - S, 1967 - 1982; F-5-2-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 5-5)
  - Research grants - S, 1967 - 1982; F-5-2-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 5-6)
  - NSERC research grants - S, 1965 - 1983; F-5-2-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 5-6)
  - Research grants - S, 1965 - 1979; F-5-2-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 5-6)
  - NSERC research grants - T, 1967 - 1978; F-5-2-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 5-6)
- Committees and meetings, 1965 - 1989; F-5-3; 88 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to the decisions, actions and activities of various departmental and faculty academic and administrative committees. The majority of files relate to the Departmental Undergraduate Curriculum Committee (DUCC) and the Departmental Graduate Studies Committee (DGSC), but see Access Points below for full list of committees represented. The series includes meeting agenda and minutes, correspondence, reports, and working papers.
  Faculty of Science. Chairmen's Meetings; Biology Articulation Committee; Canadian Committee of University Biology Chairmen; Department of Biological Sciences. Departmental Undergraduate Studies Curriculum Committee; Department of Biological Sciences. Departmental Graduate Studies Committee; Department of Biological Sciences. Ad Hoc Committee to Reivew the Undergraduate Curriculum
  - Chairmen's meetings (Faculty of Science), 1968 - 1977; F-5-3-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 5-6)
  - Chairmen's meetings (Faculty of Science), 1978 - 1981; F-5-3-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 5-6)
  - Chairmen's meetings (Faculty of Science), 1981 - 1982; F-5-3-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 5-7)
  - Biology Articulation Committee, 1969 - 1974; F-5-3-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 5-7)
  - Undergraduate Curriculum Committee, 1965 - 1972; F-5-3-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 5-7)
  - Ad Hoc Committee to Review the Undergraduate Curriculum, 1973 - 1974; F-5-3-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 5-7)
  - Ad Hoc Committee to Review the Undergraduate Curriculum, 1973 - 1974; F-5-3-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 5-7)
  - Canadian Committee of University Biology Chairmen - annual meetings, 1977 - 1979; F-5-3-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 5-8)
  - Canadian Committee of University Biology Chairmen - annual meetings, 1980 - 1983; F-5-3-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 5-8)
  - Canadian Committee of University Biology Chairmen - secretary's correspondence and surveys, 1977 - 1983; F-5-3-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 5-8)
  - Canadian Committee of University Biology Chairmen - executive, 1977 - 1980; F-5-3-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 5-8)
  - Canadian Committee of University Biology Chairmen - executive, 1980 - 1984; F-5-3-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 5-8)
  - Canadian Committee of University Biology Chairmen - general correspondence, 1977 - 1978; F-5-3-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 5-8)
  - Canadian Committee of University Biology Chairmen - general correspondence, 1979 - 1985; F-5-3-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 5-9)
  - Departmental Graduate Studies Committee - notices and items of interest, 1978 - 1980; F-5-3-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 5-9)
  - Departmental Graduate Studies Committee - correspondence, 1978 - 1980; F-5-3-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 5-9)
  - Departmental Undergraduate Studies Curriculum Committee - new courses, 1977 - 1978; F-5-3-0-0-17 (Archival box - standard 5-9)
  - Departmental Undergraduate Curriculum Committee - correspondence, 1978 - 1980; F-5-3-0-0-18 (Archival box - standard 5-9)
  - Departmental Undergraduate Curriculum Committee - minutes and papers, 1974 - 1975; F-5-3-0-0-19 (Archival box - standard 5-30)
  - Departmental Undergraduate Curriculum Committee - minutes and papers, 1974 - 1975; F-5-3-0-0-20 (Archival box - standard 5-30)
  - Departmental Undergraduate Curriculum Committee - minutes and papers, 1976 - 1977; F-5-3-0-0-21 (Archival box - standard 5-31)
  - Departmental Undergraduate Curriculum Committee - minutes and papers, 1977; F-5-3-0-0-22 (Archival box - standard 5-31)
  - Departmental Undergraduate Curriculum Committee - minutes and papers, 1978 - 1983; F-5-3-0-0-23 (Archival box - standard 5-31)
  - Departmental Undergraduate Curriculum Committee - correspondence and reports, 1978 - 1981; F-5-3-0-0-24 (Archival box - standard 5-31)
  - Departmental Undergraduate Curriculum Committee - minutes and papers, 1984 - 1985; F-5-3-0-0-25 (Archival box - standard 5-31)
  - Departmental Undergraduate Curriculum Committee - correspondence and reports, 1981 - 1983; F-5-3-0-0-26 (Archival box - standard 5-31)
  - Departmental Undergraduate Curriculum Committee - correspondence and reports, 1984 - 1985; F-5-3-0-0-27 (Archival box - standard 5-31)
  - Departmental Undergraduate Curriculum Committee - minutes and papers, 1985 - 1986; F-5-3-0-0-28 (Archival box - standard 5-32)
  - Departmental Undergraduate Curriculum Committee - minutes and papers, 1986 - 1987; F-5-3-0-0-29 (Archival box - standard 5-32)
  - Departmental Undergraduate Curriculum Committee - minutes and papers, 1987; F-5-3-0-0-30 (Archival box - standard 5-32)
  - Departmental Undergraduate Curriculum Committee - minutres and papers, 1988 - 1989; F-5-3-0-0-31 (Archival box - standard 5-32)
  - Departmental Undergraduate Curriculum Committee - transfer credits, 1982 - 1986; F-5-3-0-0-32 (Archival box - standard 5-32)
  - Departmental Undergraduate Curriculum Committee - curriculum revisions, 1980 - 1984; F-5-3-0-0-33 (Archival box - standard 5-32)
  - Departmental Undergraduate Curriculum Committee - new course proposals, 1985; F-5-3-0-0-34 (Archival box - standard 5-32)
  - Departmental Graduate Studies Committee - minutes and papers, 1977 - 1980; F-5-3-0-0-35 (Archival box - standard 5-33)
  - Departmental Graduate Studies Committee - minutes and papers, 1980 - 1982; F-5-3-0-0-36 (Archival box - standard 5-33)
  - Departmental Graduate Studies Committee - minutes and papers, 1981 - 1983; F-5-3-0-0-37 (Archival box - standard 5-33)
  - Departmental Graduate Studies Committee - minutes and papers, 1984 - 1985; F-5-3-0-0-38 (Archival box - standard 5-33)
  - Departmental Graduate Studies Committee - minutes and papers, 1985 - 1986; F-5-3-0-0-39 (Archival box - standard 5-33)
  - Departmental Graduate Studies Committee - minutes and papers, 1986 - 1987; F-5-3-0-0-40 (Archival box - standard 5-33)
  - Departmental Graduate Studies Committee - minutes and papers, 1987; F-5-3-0-0-41 (Archival box - standard 5-34)
  - Departmental Graduate Studies Committee - minutes and papers, 1988; F-5-3-0-0-42 (Archival box - standard 5-34)
- Printed materials, 1966 - 1988; F-5-4; 4 cm of textual records
  Series consists of printed and published materials relating to the promotion and advertisement of department courses, programs and activities. It includes brochures, pamphlets, and circulars; materials from the 1960s prepared by the Academic Board for Higher Education in British Columbia; the departmental newsletter Bio-Bull (1975-1976); a report by marine biology students on British Columbia as a maritime province (1975); and a report of the Behavioural Ecology Research Group on its activities for the period 1983-1988.
  Academic Board for Higher Education in British Columbia; Behavioural Ecology Research Group
  - Departmental brochures and pamphlets, 1968 - 1970; F-5-4-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 5-9)
  - Departmental newsletter - Bio-Bull, 1975 - 1976; F-5-4-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 5-9)
  - Behavioural Ecology Research Group - report, 1983 - 1988; F-5-4-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 5-9)
  - British Columbia as a Martime Province, 1975; F-5-4-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 5-9)
  - The Academic Board for Higher Education in B.C. pamphlets, 1966 - 1969; F-5-4-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 5-9)
- Departmental files, 1964 - 1985; F-5-5; 1.64 m of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to the administrative and operational activities and responsibilities of the department. These activities include relations with other departments of the university, other universities, colleges, high schools, governments, organizations, and corporations. Also documented are activities relating to enrollment, undergraduate and graduate student curricula, administrative systems and procedures, departmental policies, transfer credits, bursaries and scholarships, public relations, teaching, facilities and research. The series includes correspondence, copies of Senate minutes detailing appointments, and memoranda. For a partial list of correspondents, see Access Points below; names have been registered as access points if they appear in file titles.
  This series is a combination of two original filing systems: Departmental files from 1969-1978 and Office files from 1978-1983. A subject/organization-based numeric classification system was used to manage both sets of files. However, successive Record Centre transfers at different times has degraded the integrity and arrangement of these original file classification schemes. Some of the original block groupings for these records are evident in the series box-file lists, but no consistent attempt was made to reproduce this arrangement. The Departmental files are organized according to subject and administrative unit.
  Nelson, C. Donald; Krotkov, G.; Centre for Pest Management; University Review Committee; Radiological Safety Committee; Department of Biological Sciences. Departmental Graduate Studies Committee; National Research Committee on Marine Science; British Columbia. Ministry of Labour; TRIUMF; Atomic Energy of Canada Limited; Environment Canada; Canadian Science Secretariat; National Museums of Canada Corporation; British Columbia Institute of Technology; University Library
  - C. Donald Nelson, 1964 - 1968; F-5-5-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 5-9)
  - C.D. Nelson correspondence with G. Krotkov, 1965 - 1966; F-5-5-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 5-9)
  - Negotiated Development Grant, 1967 - 1975; F-5-5-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 5-9)
  - Phenazine patents, 1967 - 1968; F-5-5-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 5-9)
  - Policies and procedures, 1969 - 1978; F-5-5-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 5-9)
  - Pestology Centre, 1966 - 1978; F-5-5-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 5-10)
  - Annual report, 1966 - 1975; F-5-5-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 5-10)
  - Queries, 1968 - 1978; F-5-5-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 5-10)
  - University Review Committee, 1969 - 1978; F-5-5-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 5-10)
  - Radiological Safety Committee, 1966 - 1973; F-5-5-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 5-10)
  - Radiological Safety Committee, 1974 - 1977; F-5-5-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 5-10)
  - Department meetings, 1967 - 1977; F-5-5-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 5-10)
  - Electron microscope, 1968 - 1977; F-5-5-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 5-11)
  - Departmental Graduate Studies Committee, 1968 - 1978; F-5-5-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 5-11)
  - Faculty recruiting, 1967 - 1974; F-5-5-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 5-11)
  - Departmental Undergraduate Curriculum Committee, 1968 - 1978; F-5-5-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 5-11)
  - National Research Committee on Marine Science, 1968; F-5-5-0-0-17 (Archival box - standard 5-11)
  - Greenhouse, 1965 - 1977; F-5-5-0-0-18 (Archival box - standard 5-11)
  - Laboratories, 1967 - 1978; F-5-5-0-0-19 (Archival box - standard 5-11)
  - Gifts, 1967 - 1978; F-5-5-0-0-20 (Archival box - standard 5-11)